[Music]
hi everyone I'm Tanya I'm really excited
to be here today when I got the invite I
was like oh my gosh yes and so I wanted
to talk about using artificial
intelligence safely and so reing people
use it more and more which is great
totally awesome um but unfortunately not
all of us are using it super safely like
I was saying to Simon and we're doing a
lot of things that I would Define as
risky Behavior so for instance um not
checking its decisions that it's making
giving it too much agency um not
validating what we're getting back from
it putting sensitive data into it like
there's so many things that I I keep
seeing that should have oversight and
then and then we're seeing big problems
as a result and so that's why I wrote
this talk and then as I was writing it I
was like well there's actually so many
cool things that you you should also do
with it so I sort of I'm doing like
risks and how to avoid them and then
like really cool stuff that I would love
to do with it and so that is what this
talk is about and so oh yes there's me
and my name and all that so are we going
to talk about today why we need to use
AI safely
what can go wrong how to do better and
then cool ways to use AI for security
and software development at the same
time so how to do secure system
development life cycle but include AI so
that it can help you you can go faster
you can do more things be more creative
do a better job okay so who am I so I'm
Tanya Jenka I'm head of community atrap
I'm known as she hacks purple and I
really like purple there's a long story
there but you don't need to hear it
right now I've written some books so my
next book's coming out in February Alis
some Bob learn secure coding I've worked
in Tech a long time I started some
things I give some advice and I do some
research so hopefully you're like she
seems
fine we'll sit through
this I want to talk about safety so
first since chat gbt went public we have
seen so many organizations using AI
in unsafe ways like I see them just
handing over
control I see them not providing
oversight I see
them just taking whatever it is and then
blindly using it and not thinking things
through in the way that they
would like when they would do anything
else and for some reason I feel like
we're so excited about about AI that
sometimes it's almost like we've lost
our heads and we're not we're not using
the normal things that we would do when
we develop software security Now wait
wait wait I don't want us to panic
though so um if you really really really
want to get into um more edge cases
about safety I have a friend named
Darren mcke and he wrote a book called
uncontrollable and there are some people
that have fears that skynet's coming and
AI going to take over everything I'm a
lot less concerned about that but if you
wanted to dive deep go with Darren and
do that but I don't want us to panic if
anything we have this amazing new tool
you want us to celebrate it use it all
the time it but use it really really
well just like a hammer right like
hammer and nails you can also
accidentally hit your thumb if you're
not being careful right so powerful
tools we need to be safe with them don't
ask us to panic we can do this
okay so this is my favorite OSI model
with kitty cats um and this is the
outline of the talk so I'm going to talk
first about risks when using AI then I'm
going to talk about safe and effective
ways to use AI then I want to talk about
a couple of resources where you can
learn a few more things um in my new
book I I do have a a section on AI
because of course I do um but let's talk
about risk okay so we're GNA start there
so I want to break this down into a
couple different different categories
and we're going to go through them one
at a time but I kind of like to tell you
what I'm going to tell you uh and then I
tell you and then I tell you what I told
you which I realize is weird but that's
the best way to get people to remember
so I want to talk about decision- making
agency sensitive data rating code
copyright and Licensing I don't have
enough fingers validation oh yeah
validation so there's six not seven
Great okay so we're going to do six
things so I want to talk about decision
making first so risk number
one I don't feel we should allow the AI
to make decisions on behalf of our
systems without another part of the
system double-checking them so every
decision the AI makes in my opinion
should have some other piece of code not
controlled by that AI not controlled by
this and it could be I wouldn't even
want another AI to check it unless you
also have like code that a human coded
to check it um an example of this would
be like so let's say you're going
to uh give a refund to a customer right
and the AI is like blah blah blah I
think we should offer a refund then it
should go have some sort of policy check
run all the things through it and see if
it still passes and then allow the AI to
go give the refund but if it doesn't
pass be like sorry AI please
learn this is why I didn't pass policy
do better next time um it could be
changing the date of a plane tickets
deleting an account walking a
user this is funny because the AI on
stack Overflow has blocked me for life
because one day I was like so when I do
things that I just do them big I don't
know how to do small things and I was
like I'm gonna answer every single sura
question on all of stack Overflow
today was that smart not necessarily and
it didn't like some of my answers like
someone's like how can I suppress this
result and my answer was you should not
suppress it you have crossy scripting
here's how you can fix your code it got
like a lot of down
votes that's not what he
asked anyway so un block for Life by an
AI and I feel that it is an
error so we don't want to allow it to do
stuff like that because then you end up
with really nice people like Tanya job
walked from your platform forever
although I can just write them probably
and appeal it but what if it's blocking
all sorts of people by accident that it
shouldn't what if people aren't as
stubborn as me and they're not going to
write a letter and then they don't use
your platform and we don't want to let
the AI be able to make a decision on its
own related to this is agency giving the
AI agency so every single movie or the
AI take over Skynet happens the
Terminator
Etc because we give complete agency to
the AI so we should not allow the AI to
have
power over our systems our organizations
and our data so the AI should not be
able to control itself or control other
AIS right now researchers openly admit
that they do not fully understand how
the ai's model work and so that's why
they keep having hallucinations and they
want them to obviously stop having
hallucinations but they keep happening
right like lots of
interesting AI still has a big
personality how about that um and
without us being able to perfectly
understand how it works how it learns
and how it comes up with its answers I
don't believe we should allow them to
have
control uh like I feel like giving it
complete control over things is
obviously a bad judgment call right
there's a reason why we have checks and
balances in so many systems because
there has been errors in all sorts of
things and so allowing system that we
not do not fully understand to make
major decisions on our behalf is
obviously going to result in mistakes
that are easily avoidable mistakes that
aren't really complex mistakes they're
obvious mistakes and we are smarter than
this but we are already seeing this
mistake happen over and over um there is
the Air Canada chat bot that got them
into a whole bunch of hot water because
it instructed people to do a whole bunch
of things those people complained
they're like oh well we're not going to
give give you a refund it's like well
the chat bot said I could chat bot made
all sorts of decisions it
decided the system it didn't like that
policy so it overrode it for customers
and they got sued and won the rest is
news okay next wait oops there we go
sharing sensitive data with the so I
actually fell into this trap myself my
company was being Acquired and we were
about to announce it in like 2 or 3 days
and it wasn't that secret like people
had actually guessed it on social media
and I was like oh please delete that
tweet we're not supposed to tell anyone
yet so like it's not like it was a
gigantic secret but it's a pretty is a
big secret to me and I was using the AI
to try to write marketing copy because
I'm not good at that I write very casual
types of language and so I was trying to
use it to write like a formal press
release and then I realized oh my God
just sensitive information into the AI
what are we doing what if it gives that
as an answer to someone else so unless
we have permission to put the sensitive
data in the AI or we ourselves control
that AI so if you are training a model
you're a data scientist like awesome
sauce and it's your company's Ai and it
is your company's sensitive data then
you can do it but
like imagine so like imagine if it was
something more serious that you're
putting in right like what if you're so
this is common people ask the AI health
questions a whole bunch of questions
about a medical condition guess what
that any person guesses that either one
you're a medical student or a doctor
right and they can tell that very easily
from like LinkedIn and social media and
if you're not that means you are someone
you love have it or suspect you have it
right so you've just given way that all
this information and so when we ask
questions to the AI it is finding out
about us just the same as like when we
search things on Google finding things
out about us so when you go to use like
a public AI you should think about what
you're training it to know about you I
mean it definitely thinks that I want to
know what the bio for Tanya Jenka should
be and I am okay with that and it also
knows I want a lot of code samples it
probably doesn't know that I use those
code samples as what crappy code looks
like
but okay copyright and Licensing
violations so when we do copyright well
actually let me back up if you're asking
the AI to write code for you or you are
do
like you are getting it to create images
you're getting it to do work for you you
need to make sure that you own the
copyright to the thing it has created
for you because in different countries
the law is different and sometimes it
makes something for you and it's not
actually yours it's theirs another thing
is sometimes it will say here here's
this thing use this thing and if you
don't do like a reverse image search on
it or like maybe look some of that like
if you take a whole bunch of code from
it go look it up on the internet and
make sure it doesn't actually belong to
someone else because there's been
situations where it's like well the AI
gave it to me and it's like well the AI
didn't own the copyright to it and it
gave it to you and now you're using it
and you're in trouble and I'm going to
sue you and I don't mean to prejudge
things I feel like I can safely prejudge
that being sued would not be enjoyable I
feel like I can judge that all the
people on this call right now do not
want to be sued so be careful with
copyright especially if you're going to
take something directly from it and copy
it be very careful to make sure that
it's not something that they could have
taken out of a public text or image
um not validating every single thing
that it gives to you so whenever it
gives you code if you can't understand
and read that code don't use it probably
not safe just like you should not be
copying random things off of stack
Overflow or five guys from mola or
whatever all the sites on the internet
if you're just copying random things
pasting it in your code and pushing into
production that is not safe and the same
goes for the AI you need to be able to
understand what it is you just scan it
with your software composition analysis
tool and your static analysis tool and
whatever else you got going on right
like you should treat it as code written
by a junior developer who's wonderful
enthusiastic they're doing the best job
they can't but you should assume that
there are going to be mistakes in it
every single answer every single thing
it gives to you you must validate it's
wrong all the time I remember asking it
to make me a list of different companies
that used a certain security approach
and it gave me a list of 10 and I was
like oh my gosh it's going to be amazing
for the talk I'm writing and then all
the Articles were non-existent none of
the links went anywhere and then I
looked up all those people none of them
had ever talked about those things and
it had confidently presented me a giant
page of wise and I was like
no they suck so it's really really
important uh that you validate every
single thing it gives to you they like
to check things kind of over and over
and over again um like even if you've
done something five separate times in a
row and it did it correctly the sixth
time you still need to validate the
result that it gives you you can never
trust everything and as a person that
teaches secure coding all the time
that's what I teach like even if like
you know you have a front end calling an
API the API should still validate that
data because what if the front end got
taken over what if someone like used the
web proxy and interrupted it and then
sent you something it shouldn't there
like what if the input validation on the
front end just wasn't that good there's
so many things that could go wrong right
and we need to tra treat the AI in the
exact same way we need to do a zero
trust approach is it an amazing tool oh
yeah it's an absolutely Stellar
fantastic tool that I use almost every
single day um but we want to use it
safely when we are developing
one thing that is not in this
presentation that I want you to watch
out for and I kind of thought about it
after I made all my beautiful slides is
Shadow AI so Shadow it is where there's
a bunch of IT workers that aren't part
of the IT department that the business
hired because they didn't want to wait
on it or pay them or whatever and then
they usually do a whole bunch of things
that cause a mess and lots of technical
debt for everyone else because they
don't know about the policies and they
don't follow the rules and they do
whatever they want because they report
to the business Shadow AI is very
similar where someone is calling AI like
in their code there might not be a
license they might be breaking your
policy they might be running up a giant
Bill you're unaware of there could be
all sorts of problems and so if there is
a policy so first of all if there is so
go ask if there's a policy where you
work about which AI or which AI you are
allowed to use as part of software
development and check like when I was
writing my book partway through my
Publishers like you're not putting
anything in the chat gbt mate and I was
like I wouldn't unless it was a code
sample of how to do it wrong but um
because I'll get it to make the samples
for my training and then I'm like so
this is not great code why is it not
great and then I add and add and add
until it's like really good but yeah I'm
like I want to write my own book um so I
just want to mention like Shadow AI is
um it's a thing that we're seeing more
and more and you should be aware of of
it and please don't be the shadow AI or
don't implement the shadow AI like get
permission make sure you're not breaking
any policies or rules and do not create
a great big Bill that your boss is not
expecting okay so now we're on to safe
and effective fun ways to use
AI okay let's break it down writing code
vulnerabilities threat models design
comments and fixing bugs
all these are good things okay so the
first one let the AI help you write like
everything so like I said earlier so
like when I tend to write I um I tend to
write very casual language and if you've
ever read either of my books you'll know
that's very true I like to make jokes
like I was trying to explain the idea of
like polymorphism and like calling
different contexts and I was like
imagine you could call the same function
but it acts different depending upon the
context like when my mom says Miss Jacob
did you empty the dishwasher versus
normally calling me Tanya so I'm very
casual and silly when I write but
sometimes I have to write formal stuff
like a job description or um oh my gosh
there's so many different things like I
have to write a press release or or
whatever and that's not really my jam
this is where it's so great you can get
it to help you make your tone more
formal your tone well you don't get it
to make your tone more casual because
it's always weird what it writes um but
you can have it for instance you're like
here's all the things I want in my
design document like could you make a
template for me to put it into or am I
missing any of these things and it will
give you lots of ideas it can help you
write so much faster it can help you
create user stories it can help you
create any sort of project
documentation um it can help you double
check things before you're
done but remember that whatever it
drafts for you there's a strong
likelihood that there are errors or
imperfections in it so if you give it
something and ask it to rewrite it for
you always read the whole thing but um I
find that it helps me especially like I
have no more writer block ever now so
now I'll be like hey write me a blog
post about this and then I read it I'm
like this terrible blog post I've ever
written this is how it should be written
and I always end up writing the whole
thing myself but it just helps like kick
me off if that makes any sense and it
can do that for you
too the next thing I'm just going to
check my time looks like I'm doing
pretty good excellent all right um so
the next thing second there we go using
the AI to rate code
safely so I ask it to rate code all the
time like I'm like hey uh I I I want a
function that looks like this but then I
need to be able to read it and fully
understand it or I won't use it and I'm
kind of rusty in my coding to be quite
honest like I haven't developed an
Enterprise application in like a decade
but I did do it that was my full-time
job for many many many years before I
switched over into absec so I still read
lots of code but if you want a beautiful
Enterprise app probably don't want me to
write it especially the front end but
anyway I digress
so getting the AI to help you like
format your Cod like well just write
code for you is really helpful but think
of it like a junior developer you still
need to review that code need to
understand all of it and then you need
to do all the same secure system
development life cycle stuff that you
would normally do so you want to scan it
with all the scanners that you have you
want to read it with your own
eyes and you want to make sure that it
does what you expect it's so funny I was
getting it to make um code samples for
me for a training I was giving and I was
like I want a code sample that does this
and it it kept getting it wrong so it
did something completely different than
what I was describing and I ended up it
never was able to make me a sample that
did that and I had to write it all
myself from scratch but I was like like
good thing I can recode because
otherwise like I could have just copied
and pasted that and then my sample would
have made no sense because it wouldn't
have done what the training was about so
yes it can wrate code yes the code's
awesome and
helpful always double triple check
it okay next oh no why is it due to okay
using the AI to find vulnerabilities so
this is something that uh my friend
James bery showed me to do so he wrote
this blog post where he took a whole
bunch of code fed it into the AI into
Chad jbt and was like Hey can you look
for service I request fory can you look
for cross scripting and actually found
some so if you can't afford a sta
analysis tool and like I've had no
budget before but you do have access to
an AI and you are allowed to feed it
your code feed it your code and be like
yo can you try to find the OS top 10 in
here can you find this can you find that
it's not like the most practical way and
there's some open source tasss that
might do better but like you might not
be allowed access to an an open source t
for certain reasons you might not have
budget to buy one so this is sort of
like an alternative it's not a super
effective and fast way but sometimes it
finds very interesting types of
vulnerabilities there's researchers like
Jason hadex he does the wildest Things
with AI he is a
very red teamer who like I'm really glad
he's a good guy um and like he does wild
things with it and so if you are able to
train your AI to find vulnerabilities
it'll do a lot better than if you just
feed it random stuff to chap
DBT so uh number five asking the AI to
help you design so this is like a Nifty
thing that I hadn't thought of and one
of my friends did it and I was like oh
man I'm so into it so you can ask it to
help you start like designing things and
um yeah just like you tell it the thing
that you want and you describe it and
then just helps you create the design
and it sounds so silly but it never
would have occurred for me to do that
and like I don't know if any of you have
like talked to tessla about what their
product does but it kind of does that
but more and so I'm very excited about
how we're able to use it to develop
faster design faster provide better
documentation Etc and so asking it to
design again though whatever it designs
you you better follow the full system
development life cycle and like
whiteboard out that design with a
security person talk about it see if
there's some flaws in there even the
most brilliant designer can have design
flaws right because you're thinking of
how to solve a problem you're not
thinking how can I break this stuff and
that was okay was not very good at it
when I started another thing is that you
can get it to help you write comments so
I don't know about you but like when I
started my career I was great at writing
comments and then I might have got a
little lazy about it as I got older um
we don't want to write a novel let's be
clear but we do really really want to
write like comments that are effective
and helpful and so again if you are
allowed to share your code with the AI
and you should have permission before
you do that if you're writing for a
private company um if you are allowed
feed in it and be like hey write me like
a little paragraph at the top of like
what this does or write me some pseudo
code and I'm going to put it at the
bottom or whatever you can get it to add
comments to your code and like if you
like maybe are a little lazy and don't
like writing comments like I don't know
like me maybe it can be really helpful
comments are really important again no
one wants to read a novel or short story
but writing comments to me is quite
important wait wait wait wait wait wait
wait ask the AI for bug fixes so again
this means like you have already gotten
permission that you're allowed to share
your code but there's actually um like
tons of security tools right now they
have ai built into it where it'll say I
found this bug and here's what I think
is a good fix so if you don't have
access to one of those tools you can say
like listen this chunk of code according
to like my static analysis tool or the
dynamic scanner is supposed to have X
vulnerability in it how should I fix it
you might be surprised what it comes up
with it might actually be good again you
want to review that code again you want
to retest that code but like wouldn't
that be nice if it just fixed your bugs
he personally liked fixing bugs as a
developer but I know that I was in the
minority and I just realized that I did
have eight things the E thing was ask it
to help with threat modeling to me
threat modeling is the coolest I really
enjoy it and think it's very
fun um and I so basically you tell it
like I have a system that does these
things what types of threats might there
be for it um I have a system where this
talks to this what kinds of things could
go wrong and espe if you have a model
that you can train yourself it can get
smarter and smarter at figuring out
threats now some of it's threats it's
going to tell you are
like and maybe you don't want to follow
up on those and you're like those are
not very good and that's okay right but
again you just have to validate all the
results it it gives this is the same in
a real threat modeling session though
like if you're sitting there with a Dev
a security person and like a product
owner and you're talking about things
there's going to be threats where you're
like not doing that that's fine we will
accept that remote and ridiculous risk
like yes an asteroid might fall on the
AWS data
center but I don't think that we can
prevent that by redesigning our system
so I'm just gonna put that to the side
but it will come up with some cool ideas
and it might come up with things you
missed and like all the threat mod blers
say all models are wrong but some models
are useful and that's what we're trying
to do and so the AI will come up with
great ideas and then lastly be creative
so any sort of work that you're doing
think about it it's like could the AI do
this for me like sometimes I have to
write big long responses and emails and
I'm like I wonder if the AI could write
this for
me it's like what else could it do for
me that's boring like I had to write
this really super formal report for work
of quarterly business report and I wrote
all the stuff down and got all the facts
and everything and then I was like can
you make this sound super professional
like a thing aboard would would read and
then it made it sound like a hundred
times better like that sounds way more
official and fancy thank you AI so
there's lots and lots of cool stuff you
can do and so actually let me continue I
have some resources for you um but I
actually I want to summarize for a
second first we talked about risks when
using Ai and how to avoid them we
covered a bunch of things I'd really
like if you kept that in mind when
you're developing because I would really
like you to not fall over obvious
stumbling blocks there are yes there's
like wild types of attacks that people
will try to do against Ai and I
understand that but if you can do those
basic things that I covered you will be
way ahead of schedule on all the things
and then you can have like a penetration
tester come and test the edge cases for
you but if you're not doing the basic
hygiene that we do for all the other
things we do like validating our inputs
ET ET you're going to be in big trouble
with AI because it is an extraordinarily
powerful tool and so if you heed
anything from this it's proceed with
caution not without abandon like it's an
amazing fun awesome powerful great thing
that speeds us up like rocket fuel but
don't get out of control okay and now
resources yes okay so oh oh of course I
did put a conclusion oh come on okay
conclusion we learned a few things why
safety matters with when we are using AI
what risks we should look out for great
ideas on how to use AI safely and with
that now we're actually going to do
resources and I'm actually going to
follow the
agenda um so a sura Academy so they
bought my little company we have purple
and so basically it is the we have
purple Academy with a facelift and a
whole bunch extra new content and so if
you want to learn about for coding want
to learn about uh we're about to release
a security headers course because I am a
nerd that think security headers are
very cool um there's functional
programming Etc so you could check that
and it's completely
free um my books which are not free
because capitalism uh but they're not
anywhere near as expensive as some other
things in the world so I wrote some
books I am pretty biased but I think
they're pretty good my mom read some of
the first one and she said it was pretty
good there so you might like it
um cyber mentoring Monday every single
Monday on Twitter and on LinkedIn now I
do um this cyber mentoring
Monday campaign where I use this hashtag
and I try to get people to offer to
mentor and to ask for mentors and the
ideas is that someone will answer each
other they will pair off have a virtual
coffee and hopefully if things go really
well they'll have a longterm friendship
um I can't guarantee that you find a
match but I will continue to reshare you
and amplify your message week after week
until you find someone or you give up so
it usually takes two three weeks to find
someone but I do this every Monday and I
have since 2018 and I don't pick the
mentor for you because I'm a terrible
Matchmaker but I'm a great connector and
so check that out if you are interested
in basically putting jet fuel in your
career um tldr SE so my friend clarent
writes this newsletter it is free it is
every week and I know lots of
newsletters summarize the news he does
not do that he summarizes the security
research from that week and so obviously
I read the aback section right and I
always read the cute story at the top
and so he covers like many many many
different topics and his newsletter is
free and I was like I'm gonna add it
because I really like it and my
audiences might find it helpful and then
lastly resources me um so I have a
YouTube channel a Twitter a BL Blue Sky
a LinkedIn a my gosh I have a lot of
stuff um I don't have Instagram that's a
lie I should remove that but um yeah I
do a lot of things and if you want this
can be the beginning of a very long-term
relationship um I give a lot away I give
away a lot of things for free I talk a
lot I write a lot and so um I want to
thank everyone for coming today to this
amazing conference and I want to thank
Tesla for having me because this has
been so
yeah I'm wondering if there's any
questions that we're going to have in
the chat amazing yeah we have only a
short time uh for chat first of all
mentoring idea is so lovely and I know
you've been doing this for many many
years now and this is it's it's an
amazing thing and I've seen you absolute
retweet and and and really share those
so um T's not just saying that this is
this is this is a real thing so please
please do get involved with that um a
nice fun question here what's the most
surprising thing you've asked AI to do
which you thought would be a breeze for
it but but it couldn't do or it got it
wrong I asked it if it would try to
write a bio for me and I said list my
accomplishments and it listed wild
things I did not do and did not list
lots of things that are very public yeah
like it seems to think I made a video
game I have corrected it I have not made
a video game well I did in college but
not really you know what I mean I didn't
so you did so you did
like we made like a little puzzle like I
wouldn't I wouldn't say it like things
you made in college don't count so it
wrote like a really wacky bio that I was
like like none of that's true um but it
did not say I was an American and so I'm
Canadian as the accent that you hear and
I've had a lot of sites online say I'm
American and I'm like can't you see how
I say
[Laughter]
about amazing so it got that right and
it got everything else wrong
one thing I will say actually Tanya is I
think um based on some of the the things
that you that you mentioned I think we
as developers who love writing code Rush
too quickly into the how can it help me
write code or how can it help me do this
when actually one of the things that AI
is really good at is doing things that
we don't necessarily enjoy doing and and
we I feel like we should sometimes take
things away from us that we just don't
dedicate time to and two of the things
that I loved that you that you said was
threat modeling right how little threat
modeling gets done by by devs naturally
and things like that oh I didn't know
they did that look at that um how how
how few are things gone see if it works
for
you no I don't get to have it or I get I
get one maybe it was just maybe I just
have to have one no it doesn't it
doesn't enjoy my thumbs no no is
asleep wow look at that amazing right so
sorry we dig
um yeah threat modeling and design I
think those are two things that that
that we don't spend enough time on or we
don't put enough imagination into
sometimes and I think that's actually
those are the areas that that it can be
done documentation is another I must say
comments I don't know part of me was
like oh yeah we definitely don't do a
good enough job about that but I don't
know if AI personally I don't know if AI
will will give the right comments into
code but all of these things are are
absolutely um are absolutely valid one
thing I'll say before we um before we do
we do finish um absolutely amazing talk
as always do check out Tanya's books I
have one I didn't realize there was a
second I have one and I really really
enjoyed it so please please please uh do
check out Alice and Bob as well so um
great great books Tanya thank you so so
much for for joining us um for joining
us on on the IR native Devcon um always
a pleasure to see you and and hear you
hear you uh teach and talk so thank you
so so much
thank you so much for having me and I
can't wait to watch all the talks that I
missed throughout the day amazing thank
you see you again soon